A Guide to the Correspondence and Subject Files of the Librarian of Virginia, 1832-2024 Jan
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Correspondence and Subject Files of the Librarian of Virginia, 1832-2024 Jan
The Library of Virginia
28078, 28117, 28179, 28366, 28480, 28771, 30470, 31312, 31641, 31999, 32336, 33057, 34229, 34710, 35146, 37403, 37564, 37767, 40565, 41116, 41207, 41208, 41543, 43385, 44953, 50466, 50523, 54082
83.05 cu. ft. (250 Boxes)
Office of the Librarian of Virginia
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 28078, was transferred from the Main Office, Virginia State Library, Richmond, Virginia, 22 August 1973.
Accession 28117, was transferred by the State Librarian's Office, 30 March 1973.
Accession 28179, was transferred from the Main Office, Virginia State Library, Richmond, Virginia, 22 January 1974.
Accession 28366, was transferred by the State Librarian's Office, 11 September 1974.
Accession 28480, was transferred from the Main Office, Virginia State Library, 9 December 1974.
Accession 28771, was transferred by the State Librarian's Office, 17 October 1976.
Accession 30470, was transferred by the State Librarian's Office, 30 June 1979.
Accession 31312, was transferred by the State Librarian's Office, 19 January 1982.
Accession 31641, was transferred by the State Librarian's Office, 14 January 1983.
Accession 31999, was transferred by the State Librarian's Office, 23 February 1984.
Accession 32336, was transferred by the State Librarian, 12 March 1985.
Accession 33057, was transferred by the State Librarian's Office, 16 May 1988.
Accession 34229, was transferred by the State Library records manager, 26 August 1992.
Accession 35146, was transferred by the State Librarian's Office, 8 November 1996.
Accession 34710, was transferred by State Library records manager, 29 August 1994.
Accession 37403, no acquisition information available, this collection was retrospectively accessioned, 9 June 2000.
Accession 37564, no acquisition information available, this collection was retrospectively accessioned, 15 August 2000.
Accession 37767, was transferred by the Librarian of Virginia's Office, 17 November 2000.
Accession 40565, was transferred by Librarian of Virginia's Office, 28 April 2003.
Accession 41116, was transferred by Librarian of Virginia's Office, 22 March 2004.
Accession 41207, was transferred by Librarian of Virginia's Office, 24 May 2004.
Accession 41208, was transferred by Librarian of Virginia's Office, 24 May 2004.
Accession 41543, was transferred by the Librarian of Virginia's Office, 9 November 2004.
Accession 43385, was transferred by the Librarian of Virginia's Office, 26 July 2007.
Accession 44953, no acquisition information available, this collection was retrospectively accessioned, 5 May 2010.
Accession 50466, no acquisition information available, this collection was retrospectively accessioned, 26 June 2012.
Accession 50523, no acquisition information available, this collection was retrospectively accessioned, 25 July 2012.
Accession 54082 was transferred by the Office of the State Librarian, 22 January 2024.
Accruals
The Library of Virginia has multiple accessions for the correspondence and subject files of the Librarian of Virginia and will continue to receive accruals for this ongoing series.
Historical Information
For many years, The Library of Virginia had no definitive home. Valuable early records were kept at Jamestown as early as 1676 and were then moved to the College of William and Mary for a brief period at the century's end. By 1780, extant records were moved to the Capitol in Richmond.
Coincidentally, in 1779, the Virginia General Assembly was presented among its legislation, "A Bill for Establishing a Public Library" drawn up by Thomas Jefferson. The Bill provided for 2000 pounds yearly to be expended to maintain a State Library in Richmond. The facility was to be a reference library only without books being lent for home use. Perhaps ahead of its time, the bill failed to pass.
The Virginia State Library was created by an act passed by the General Assembly on January 23, 1823, to establish a public library with funds derived from the sale of William W. Hening's THE STATUTES AT LARGE. From 1823 to 1828, the Library was under the control of the governor and council. In 1828, the General Assembly created a joint committee on the library (located in a room in the southeastern corner of the Capitol) to oversee its administration. Use of the State Library was restricted to members of the state government in a policy that continued until at least 1856. The Secretary of the Commonwealth served ex officio as state librarian from 1832 to 1903.
The growth of the State Library was somewhat erratic. Book holdings increased from 1,313 in 1828 to 17,480 in 1856. Lack of funds and politics frequently intermingled to slow library development. General W. H. Richardson, State Librarian in 1852, became embroiled in an effort to remove him "to make way for some politician of democratic principles." At the close of Reconstruction, Dr. George William Bagby, then State Librarian, was terminated and his position abolished at the hands of Readjusters.
Eventually, on May 15, 1903, the General Assembly passed an act that created a library board to administer the library, authorized the deposit of public records in the library, provided for the publication of historical records by the library, and established a library fund for the purchase of books and private papers. The Library Board, which was responsible for naming the State Librarian, was itself appointed by the Board of Education. The General Assembly passed an act on March 29, 1944, transferring the power to appoint the Library Board to the governor.
While many public records somehow survived the Commonswealth's early years, many losses occurred due to fires, the ravages of war and negligence. When the library was moved, for example, in 1895 to a building separate from the Capitol, "chutes were constructed from the upper story of the Capitol to facilitate the delivery of books to the wagons of the junk dealer who had bought them." The move was poorly planned and the library's contents suffered great loss at the hands of those very authorities assigned to protect them.
The new facility quickly was found to be inadequate and efforts were made both in 1910 and 1920 to construct a proper building for the State Library and its collections. Ground was broken for a new facility on December 7, 1938. At last, on December 23, 1940, the newly completed Virginia State Library was opened to the public.
The Virginia State Library adopted the name, the Virginia State Library and Archives, in early 1987 to more adequately reflect its mission and purpose. On July 1, 1994 the name was changed to The Library of Virginia, evocative of the Library of Congress. In 1997 the library moved to it's fourth and current location, the 800 block of East Broad Street.
The title of State Librarian has been held by: John Pendleton Kennedy (1903-1906), Henry Read McIlwaine (1907-1934), Wilmer L. Hall (1935-1947), Randolph W. Church (1948-1970), Donald R. Haynes (1971-1984), Ella Gaines Yates (1985-1990), Dr. John C. Tyson (1991-1994), Nolan T. Yelich (1995-2007), and Sandra Gioia Treadway, 2007 July-2024 Jan. The current State Librarian, Dennis T. Clark, took office January 25, 2024.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of multiple accessions and includes, but is not limited to, incoming and outgoing correspondence, subject files, memorandums, invitations, newsletters, reports, invoices, and receipts. Correspondents include, but are not limited to, library board members, state and federal agencies, book and manuscript dealers, supply vendors, library associations, universities, historical societies, as well as, staff and patrons. While this series spans over 100 years, topics remain similar: budgets, policies and procedures, collection development, donations, acquisitions, patron requests, publications, building requirements and statistics. Correspondence is both handwritten and typed. Each accession is described in more detail within the finding aid.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files
Contents List
- Correspondence and Subject Files, 1827-2007.
  - 1827-1887 (Accession 44953)., 2 cu. ft. (8 boxes)
    The correspondence in this collection was sent to several secretaries of the Commonwealth serving as state librarian including William H. Richardson, George W. Munford, & J. M. Herndon. Correspondents include E.L. Carey & A. Hart, booksellers in Philadelphia; P.H. Nicklin & T. Johnson, booksellers in Philadelphia; John S. Meehan, Librarian of Congress; Henry S. Tanner, map maker; Francis H. Smith, Superintendent of the Virginia Military Institute; Peachy R. Grattan, author of Grattan's Virginia Reports; Alexandre Vattemare, Agent of the Commonwealth for International Literary Exchanges; and others. Noteworthy correspondence includes the following: Peter Cottom, bookseller & publisher in Richmond, re. a dispute with the State Librarian concerning the sale of Randolph's Reports (1838 Mar. 6); William Y. Sturman, Westmoreland County, re. the portrait of Lord Chatham hanging in the court room (1833 June 26); B. Shreve, Jr., re. the sale of Col. James Monroe's property including his library for the use of the state (1836 Mar. 18); William H. Cabell, Lewisburg, re. the purchase of books for the library of the Court of Appeals (1836 July 21); John S. Meehan, Librarian of Congress, re. the purchase of "Warden's Biblioteca America" (1837 May 18); John S. Meehan re. journals of the House & Senate of Virginia (1837 June 21); Henry S. Tanner, Philadelphia, re. orders from the King of France for a map of Virginia (1838 Dec. 17 & 26); Francis H. Smith, Superintendent of the Virginia Military Institute, re. common schools (1843 Dec. 29); B.W. Leigh, Richmond, re. payment for his reports which were appropriated by the Legislature on 26 March 1842 (1843 Jan. 17); William H. Richardson to Alexandre Vattemare re. the exchange of publications (1845 Aug.); Peachy R. Gratton re. copyright of the Virginia Reports owned by the state (1845 June 4); Alexandre Vattemare, Paris, re. the transfer of documents & maps (1846 Nov. 30);William Y. Sturman, Clerk of Westmoreland County, re. the portrait of Lord Chatham (1847 Dec. 21); Alexandre Vattemare, Richmond, encl. a list of the states & scientific establishments of Europe to exchange books, maps, etc., with Virginia (1848 Nov. 2); C. Crozet, Civil Engineer, re. a proposal to make a new map of Virginia (1849 Feb. 14); John S. Meehan, Librarian of congress, re. their classification system (1849 Feb. 20); Alexandre Vattemare, Paris, re. the forwarding of the national publication "La Galerie Nationale de Versailles" (1850 Dec. 26); Joseph Henry, Secretary of the Smithsonian Institute, encl. official acknowledgment of receipt of publications from the state of Virginia (1851 Feb. 25); Alexandre Vattemare, Paris, re. the transmission of a map of France & other publications (1851 June 27); C.C. Jewett, Librarian of the Smithsonian Institute, sending "Notices of Public Libraries in the U.S." (1851 July 9); Alexandre Vattemare, Paris, re. an appropriation of $300 for the support of the agency in Paris (1851 Aug. 27); Alexandre Vattemare, Paris, encl. a catalogue of works presented to Virginia by the French government (1851 Oct. 14); Governor Bringham Young, Utah Territory, acknowledging receipt of acts of the Assembly of Virginia (1853 Oct. 6); Lyman C. Draper, Madison, WI., re. the nomination of William H. Richardson as an honorary member of the State Historical Society of Wisconsin and requesting a set of Hening's Statutes at Large (1854 Mar. 4); Alexandre Vattemare, Paris, re. the exchange of publications from France (1854 June 10); John M. Seigfried to the Secretary of Virginia requesting signatures of Masonic autograph letters including George Wythe, Richard Henry Lee, Benjamin Harrison, & others (1855 Jan. 29); George W. Munford to John Seigfried, Easton, PA, re. sending him signatures of notable Virginians from old documents (1855 Mar. 16); John B. Floyd, Secretary of War, forwarding copies of the General Regulations of the Army for the Virginia milita (1857 May 12); George W. Munford, Secretary of the Commonwealth, to Alexandre Vattemare re. receipt of four parcels of seeds from France & grape cuttings from the vinyard of the Imperial Jardin Du Luxombourg (1859 Mar. 19); and Jacob Thompson, Secretary of the Interior, submitting copies of the laws of Congress (1859 May 25).
    Additional noteworthy documents include the following: a report of the committee appointed to select a room for the Public Library & prepare rules (incl. rules & regulations of the Library) (1828 Nov. 4); a list of fines received from the commencement of the Library to 31 December 1829 (1829 Dec. 31); a catalogue of books to be purchased for the Virginia Library (1830); a report of the State Librarian suggesting creating agencies for the sale of books & maps belonging to the Library Fund (1830 Jan. 7); a statement that the Librarian should be constituted selling & purchasing agent and authorized to dispose of the books & maps constituting the Library Fund (1831); an agreement between William H. Richardson and Colin & Nowlan, printers, for copies of reports of the Court of Appeals & General Court by Peachy R. Gratton (1832 June 18); a petition of the New York Historical Society requesting copies of the laws of Virginia (1840 Dec. 1); a report of the Joint Committee of the Senate & House of Delegates appointed to examine the Library (1840 & 1841); a contract between William H. Richardson and Shepherd & Colin, printers, to print, bind, secure copyright, & deliver seven hundred copies of a volume of reports of the Court of Appeals (1842 Sept.,1844 Jan. 30, Nov. 1, & 1845 Nov. 1); a report of the Joint Committee of the Senate & House of Delegates appointed to examine the Library containing the 5th section of the act of February 1830 which placed the Library Fund under the control of the joint committee and made it their duty to receive the reports of the Librarian, examine & settle library accounts, and prescribe rules for the good order, preservation, & police of the library (1843); a report of William H. Richardson re. the sale at auction of various books & maps (1843 Mar. 3); a resolution of the General Court to remove the law books from the State Library to the State Courthouse or to provide a law library there (1847 Dec. 11); a catalogue of purchases (1847); a list of maps, books, engravings, etc., presented to the state of Virginia through Alexandre Vattemare (1848 Nov. & 1849); a resolution of the Joint Committee of the House & Senate that one of the alcoves in the gallery of the Library be set apart for the books which have been presented to the state of Virginia under the system of international exchanges originated by Alexandre Vattemare (1849 Feb. 16); a resolution of the Joint Committee of the House & Senate re. the accounts of the librarian & the necessity of enlarging the accommodations by removing the office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth (1851); receipts of clerks of localities for copies of acts of the Legislature (1853); an agreement between George W. Munford, Secretary of the Commonwealth, & William F. Ritchie, Public Printer, to print, bind, secure copyright, & deliver one thousand copies of a volume of Reports of the Court of Appeals by Peachy R. Gratton (1853 Oct. 7); and a contract of William F. Ritchie, Public Printer, to print one thousand copies of volume 11 of the Court of Appeals by Peachy R. Gratton (1855 Apr. 10).
    Arranged chronologically.
    - 1827 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1828 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Jan-June 1829 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - July-Dec 1829 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Jan-May 1830 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - June-Nov 1830 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dec 1830 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jan-Sept 1831 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Oct-Dec 1831 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1832 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1833 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1834 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1835 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1836 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1837 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Jan-Sept 1838 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Oct-Dec 1838 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1839 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1840 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1841 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1842 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1844 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1845 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1846 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1847 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1848 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 1849 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - 1850 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1851 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1852 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Jan-July 1853 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Aug-Dec 1853 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Jan-July 15 1854 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - July 17-Sept 1854 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Oct-Dec 1854 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Jan-July 1855 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Aug-Dec 1855 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1856 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Jan-Aug 1857 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Sept-Dec 1857 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Vouchers (No. 1-68) 1857 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Jan-Aug 1858 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Sept-Dec 1858 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Jan-June 1859 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - July-Dec 1859 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Vouchers (No. 1-105) 1859 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - 1860 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - 1861 - Vouchers (No. 1-86) (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - 1864-1869 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - 1869 - Vouchers (No. 1-149) (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - 1870-1887 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 1827-1829 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1830-1832 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 1834-1849 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 1850-1855 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 1856-1858 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 1859-1866 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 1832-1902 (Accession 37564)., .45 cu. ft. (1 box).
    This collection contains the correspondence and subject files of the Librarian of Virginia. Included are correspondence, memoranda, notes, receipts, and vouchers.
    Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
    - Administrative Papers, 1865-1893. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1860-1901. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Listing of Virginia Counties, 1832. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Memoranda, 1880. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Notebooks, undated. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Notes Regarding Collections, 1866-1895. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Receipts, 1859-1902. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Vouchers, 1859-1960. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1865-1869 (Accession 37767)., .55 cu. ft. (1 box)
    This collection contains invoices, receipts and notes, as well as inventories of government documents on hand at the State Library, which, were in turn sold or disbursed, including Henning's Statues at Large.
    The guide has been arranged alphabetically by folder title.
    - Lists of Government Documents on hand, sold or disbursed, 1865-1869. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Notes, 1865-1869. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Receipts and Invoices, 1865-1867. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1877-1912 (Accession 37403)., .7 cu. ft. (2 boxes)
    This collection is comprised of reports, clippings, correspondence related to the State Library as well as materials related to the School Book Investigation which included an investigation into the acquisition of materials for the Travelling Library. This collection contains correspondence, reports and newsclippings related to the library and its activities. Included are a draft of an annual report, an inventory of the Archives Room (date unknown) as well as materials regarding some of the controversies that have surrounded the library. Included here are materials related to the loss of items in the collections (1912), the condition of the library building (1912), and the sale of collection materials (1895). It also contains correspondence, reports, newsclippings, and court transcripts relating to the School Book Investigation. The School Book Investigation focused on purchasing practices employed in the acquisition of textbooks and also books for the Travelling Library. Mr. J.P. Kennedy, State Librarian, was under investigation in this affair, and his correspondence with publishers is found in this series. Oversize materials may be found in Box 2.
    - Annual Report to the Committee on the Library and the General Assembly (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Articles regarding loss of materials and condition of the library building (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Collection information - Archives Room (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Illinois State Library Policies (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Sale of Books, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Va. Colonial Records Project - Correspondence and Reports (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Appendix: Being comparative prices of school books and various exhibits not copied in body of evidence (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Committee hearing transcripts in the legislative investigation for the school book (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, invoices and other materials used as evidence, 1906-1907, fo. 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, invoices and other materials used as evidence, 1906-1907, fo. 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Library fund (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Papers returned by Mr. Thomas E. Owen after copying in the proceedings of investigation of the Library Board in March 1907 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Proceedings of the third session of the School Book hearings, February 5, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lists of library purchases since 1877 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1879-1992; Bulk 1975-1990 (Accession 34229)., 23 cu. ft. (23 boxes)
    This collection contains the correspondence of the State Librarians, Henry R McIlwaine, Randolph W. Church, Donald R. Haynes, and Ella Gaines Yates, as well as, Assistant State Librarian, Wilmer Hall, Ray O. Hummel, and Nolan T. Yelich, and State Archivist Morgan P. Robinson, and Louis Manarin. Correspondents include but are not limited to; libraries, universities, patrons, state government, the American Library Association, the Virginia Library Association, the National Commission on Libraries and Information Science, and the National Endowment for the Humanities. Topics include; the audit of Lonesome Pine Regional Libraries, the establishment of the Virginia Center of the Book, the Colonial Records Project, Southeastern Library Network, State art collection, new library building plans, historical highway markers, Virginia Cavalcade and the Virginia State Library crisis. Included are building plans, surveys, newsletters, invitations, grants, calendars, reports, mass mailings and brochures.
    - A (letters), 1988. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Accidents, 1988. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Accounting, 1990. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Accounting, 1990. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Accounting, 1988. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Accounting, 1987. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Acid Free Paper, 1990 Apr 2. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Administration, 1988. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Administration Work Order Purchases, 1985-1988. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Administration: General Services, 1985-1986. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Administration: Services Division, 1988. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Administrative Meanings, undated. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Administrative Law Appendix, 1989-1990. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Affirmative Action Plan, 1987-1989. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Aids, 1988 May 10. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - American Library Association (ALA), 1987-1990. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - ALA - Accreditation, 1990 Mar 19. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - ALA - Legislation, 1985-1988. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - ALA - Legislation, 1981-1987. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - ALA - Yearbook, 1985-1986. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Alabama Public Library Service, 1988 Mar 3. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - ALANET, 1989 Jan 25. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - ALOHA, 1988. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Anderson, Alain, 1980-1985. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Annual Program, 1989-1990. (Box 1, Folder 25)